[Music]
Stanford
University I I say okay let me read to
you from uh from the first uh from the
first
um paragraph statistical mechanics is
often thought of as a theory of how
atoms combined to form gases liquid
solids and even plasmas in black body
radiation but it is both more and less
than that statistical mechanics is a
useful tool in many areas of Science in
which a large number of variables have
to be dealt with using statistical
methods my son who studies neural
networks uses it in fact about uh about
six months ago he called me up and says
a uh pop do you uh you ever hear of this
thing called the partition
function and uh yeah I heard of it and
he said I'm just learning about it now
because uh we use it in the statistical
properties of neural networ
Works uh free energy all those Concepts
that uh you know one often thinks of in
the context of um of physics but it's a
much broader set of ideas than that so
let me just continue with reading I have
no doubt that some of the financial
Wizards that AIG and Layman Brothers
used
it so that was just to uh to reinforce
what you asked me about derivatives
right saying that statistical mechanics
is the theory of gases is rather like
saying calculus is the theory of
planetary
orbits really what it is is it's a
mathematical structure it's a
mathematical structure which of course
has
applications and if I had to put it in a
nutshell in a very brief nutshell
statistical mechanics is simply
probability Theory now I personally have
never understood the difference between
statistics and probability I'm so told
to some technical
difference I guess there probably is but
I don't know that
difference uh but statistical mechanics
is the application of probability well
statistical mechanics is probability
Theory it may be applied to lots and
lots of different situations but it's
probability Theory under
certain specific
circumstances so I want to talk about
those circumstances a little bit first
oh uh as I understand it the um the
statistics is the purely mathematical
part that um it doesn't depend on
whether or not the mapping to reality
connects so with probabilities you are
trying to do something where you
predicting behavior of something okay so
if you're right and I I have no reason
to think you're not um and I understood
exactly what you said uh statistical
mechanics is a mathematical
structure okay so I suppose in that
sense it's
statistics uh the question is under what
circumstances does it apply to reality
and I want to talk about that a little
bit but the real answer is very very
difficult and I think to my knowledge it
has never been completely sorted out and
proved in absolute rigor that uh
statistical mechanics as we Define it
actually applies to any serious
significant system uh other than some
very simple model
systems but it's interesting to think
about what are the criteria and what are
the circumstances under which
statistical mechanics as we normally
think about it applies to systems to
systems like a piece of chalk
let's hope let's hope
pray ah
good it
works so let's start with coin flipping
coin flipping you have a coin which has
heads and tails and ordinarily under
ordinary circumstances you would say
that the probability for flipping a head
is a half and the probability of
flipping a tail is a half they have
equal probabilities and the
probabilities sum to one so therefore
it's a half and a half what right do you
have to say that how can you prove that
uh well one simple argument which is
rather
convincing is that coins are symmetric
apart from some little detailed uh
differences between the two sides of the
coin and in fact of course because of
the difference between the two sides of
the coin it's not absolutely true that
uh the the probability is a half and a
half one side May weigh a little more
you know the mass distribution is
slightly imbalanced because on one side
The Carving is a little bit different
than the other but forget
that resist yeah air resistance could
have but if a coin was a really Fair
coin it means that it's so
symmetric uh that you for the purposes
of flipping the coin the two sides are
exactly the same somehow you can look at
it and tell which is which that's true
but uh the paint that distinguishes the
two of them is so thin or the carving or
whatever that doesn't make any
difference the Symmetry between the two
sides of the coin ensure that the
probabilities have to be the same and
once they're the same it has to be a
half a half right okay so that's that's
straightforward there's a kind of notion
of a priori probability a priori uh
probability in this case because there
is a
symmetry let me give you another example
let's take a d dye is in
dice uh and let's color the faces of the
dye I want to color them rather than
number them for no no no important
reason all right so there are six sides
to a die and let's color them red yellow
blue
green
orange
purple okay now again the six sides of
the coin not the coin the six sides of
the Dy are SYM
symmetric there's a symmetry operation
of just turning the die through 90°
about various
axes uh which takes any configuration of
the Dy into some other configuration and
that symmetry again ensures if you
believe that the Dy is really symmetric
if you believe that the die is symmetric
enough then you're forced to believe
that the answer answer is that the
probability of getting a let us say red
or any other one of the colors is
one6 right and uh that's a good argument
but in most situations there aren't such
symmetries so if there aren't such
symmetries is there a notion to back you
up from where you can start your
starting point for discussion of
probabilities a starting point which you
can think of as a priori
probabilities the answer is not
obviously but uh let's talk about it a
little bit in particular let me give you
a ridiculous kind of example let's
suppose I decided to take the
d and color
it by replacing purple by
Red it now has five colors
red red yellow and so forth it now has
five colors now if I just write down the
five colors and you stare at them you
would have no reason to believe that
there's not a symmetry among them just
writing them down one after another uh
of course one has more letters than the
other but that's not the point you could
number them if you liked uh you would
say you might say look I have five
possibilities red yellow blue
green oh there it is green and
orange so what's the probability of
flipping a red and the answer by the
same logic or illogic would be 1/5 but
you know perfectly well that's not the
answer yeah um can't uh information
Theory make this rigorous by by defining
the entropy
functional well we're we're going to
spend a lot of time doing exactly that
but no no uh in principle yes but in
fact systems are too complicated to
easily prove that the
conditions uh for thermal equilibrium
and so forth really apply most systems
are too complicated there's a few model
systems that you can actually prove the
theorems about but uh uh in principle
you can State the conditions but it's
very very hard to uh to prove them in
any case here you have five colors and
if you didn't know any better and you
didn't know very much about the D you
would say that's one and five but of
course the answer is not one in five the
answer is two and six for red and one
and six for yellow blue green and
orange
so what's going on well the answer of
course is that the real symmetry of the
system acts on the six faces not on the
five
colors but it's very easy to imagine
that a diey doesn't have a symmetry it
doesn't have any symmetry at all it
could be weighted in some way that's
sort of off balance it could be an
unfair
die uh
weighted with extra weight in one corner
or something like
that and then where would you get your a
priori probability from well of course
one way of getting the a priori
probability would just be to flip it a
zillion times and uh after a zillion uh
flips you could uh count how many of
each kind you got but that's not what
we're going to do we're not going to try
to study this air in this room by doing
a zillion replicas of the room I mean we
will do that mathematically but not
physically and uh so someplace else we
have to get the basic ideas of a priori
probability
from
uh you might uh go back a step and say
if the D is not really a fair
die then the probability is going to
depend or may depend on all kinds of
things it may depend on details such as
the way the hand flips it the air
currents in the room the nature of the
surface that it may or may not bounce
off all kinds of details which are
extraneous to the system itself in other
words it may depend on the environment
as well as the system
[Music]
uh so the idea of an a priority
probability for the die may not be such
a good idea after
all
uh you haven't mentioned the fact that
you've implicitly assumed a time centry
in which you can you can repace we we
are going to implicitly assume time
Symmetry and in fact and in fact we're
going to talk about that uh sort of
right
now let's uh let's add a dynamical
element to the idea which may help us
get a handle on this idea of a priori
probability the the cube here the D
let's think of it as a dynamical system
a dynamical system means one which
changes with time under some law of
motion a law of motion is simply an
updating process it tells you if you
know the state of the system at one
instant of time it tells you what the
instant what the state will be in the
next instant of time that's the idea of
a law of motion an updating from one
instant to the next now of course with
the motion of particles and things like
that the motion is nice and smooth and
continuous and you can subdivide the
time into uh into Infinite tmal elements
but if we're talking about a d the
closest thing we could imagine to that
is that the D execut UT
operations one per now per what per
Elementary time interval in other words
we imagine dividing up time into equal
segments we will not take the limit and
each instant uh the die rearranges
itself in a way that only depends on
what's showing at the top of the
D okay so we could represent that law
and in this in previous versions of this
class we have talked about this kind of
thing several times but you can
represent the motion of a die as a rule
okay so let's see I have some rules
written down here let me give you some
rules here's the first
one if the top of the die is red then in
the next instant let's see where is it
uh
yeah red goes to
Blue if it's blue blue goes
to
Yellow if it's yellow yellow goes to
Green if it's green green goes to Orange
and if it's
orange orange goes to purple and if it's
purple purple goes back to
Red we could represent this as a kind of
diagram we could put the
six colors down
red
blue yellow
green orange purple and then just draw
some arrows red goes to blue blue goes
to yellow yellow goes to Green Green
goes to Orange Orange goes to purple
purple goes back to
Red okay that would be a complete
dynamical theory of a very very simple
system the dice the
D okay now supposing the um the Motions
occurred quickly let's suppose they
happened fast so fast that they happen
let's say in less than a blink of an
eye and now we ask I don't care whether
the Dy is weighted funny or not weighted
funny it doesn't matter this is the
rules this is the rules of motion of the
Dy and it spends equal amounts of time
at each in between each successive
motion then it's pretty darn clear that
if I just randomly sample it at an
instant of time as it's going from one
to the other very fast if I randomly
sample it it's pretty darn clear that I
will have an equal probability of
getting any one of the six 1 2 3 four
five 1 two 3 four five six colors right
just because they each spend the same
amount of time or each uh the die spends
the same amount of time being in each
one of these states so it's pretty darn
clear I don't think I need to prove it
that this would be a situation in which
uh
uh the probability would be one six as
you would expect now this is fairly
robust we could replace this law by
other laws let's see I have another one
I think I have two others written down
well we could just replace
Blue by green and green by Blue and
maybe change some other ones wouldn't
make any difference so there are many
possible laws like this all of which
would lead to the same one
six so it's fairly robust in a sense but
is it completely robust no I'll give you
an example of a law which gives a
different answer or it doesn't give an
answer all together really that's the
point okay so here it is
red goes to
blue blue let's see what do I have here
blue goes to
green and green goes back to
red yellow goes to
purple purple goes to what have I left
out orange and orange goes back to
Yellow all right now at every stage
whatever the state of the system is it
tells you what to do next there's
nothing wrong with this rule it does
have the funny a funny property relative
to this one over here what is that funny
property well maybe the easiest way two
orbits it has two
orbits this has one orbit this has two
orbits or two cycles you might say
Cycles in fact if you graft it you've
grafted it you might red
blue
green back to red and
yellow to
purple to
Orange back to Yellow two distinct
Cycles now there's no way a
priority to know what the probability is
that you're on this cycle or that cycle
if you're on this cycle and you know
you're on this cycle and you whip around
it real fast then obviously the
probability is oneir to be red blue or
green and zero to be yellow purple or
orange but on the other hand all you may
have is also statistical knowledge where
it came from let's not worry about now
about whether you're on this cycle or
this
cycle and that in that case it would be
more complicated I'll leave it to you to
calculate if it was of course if it was
a half a half probability of a half for
this and a half for that then you would
reduce yourself back to 16 but if it was
probability 1/3 to be on this cycle and
2/3 to be on that cycle then it would be
more complicated I'm not going to work
it out right now okay so this is a
counter example to the statement that
there's equal a priori probabilities for
all
configurations but this system or with
this law of nature this law law of
motion there is something called a
conserved quantity all right let's let's
define a quantity z z is for zilch this
is the zilch the zilch has a value
either one or zero it's equal to
one
for red blue or
green and the zil is equal to zero
for yellow purple or
orange two distinct orbits with two
distinct values of the zilch the zilch
is conserved what does it mean that it's
conserved if it starts at a particular
value it stays at that value
endlessly so a conservation
law in this context and really in all
contexts means that the system breaks up
into different orbits with different
values of the conserved quantity there
may be many conserved quantities for a
complicated
system and you have you you have two
possibilities one is to fix the zilch
you measure it you know what it is if
you know what it is then you just throw
away all the other values and you go
back to a somewhat smaller system in
this case a system with three states but
just repeat the story and there will be
equal a priori probabilities of the all
of the states with the same value of the
conserved quantum number with Ser with
the conserved
quantities um and as I said the other
possibility is you may only know
statistical information about these
things in which case you use that
statistical information but statistical
information about the values of
conserved
quantities what's the most important
conserved quantities in physics well
energ is going to be the most important
one for us momentum is not going to play
such a big role and the reason momentum
doesn't play a big role is because
usually we're thinking
about
systems which are contained within
containers in statistical mechanics
we're usually thinking about gases or
liquids or whatever it is contained in
containers and of course when a molecule
hits the wall it bounces off of course
it gives a little bit of momentum to the
box but we don't care that much about
the Box uh we don't we don't try to keep
track if I throw a um uh tennis ball
against the
wall we don't have to remember that the
earth recoils a little bit it doesn't
play any role in what goes on with the
tennis ball it's not important and so if
we ignore the recoil of the box then
momentum is not conserved by virtue of
hitting the sides of the
box so momentum is not so important
electric charge can be a very important
conserved
quantity angular momentum angular
momentum is much like linear momentum
also tends not to play a big role in
general but it could I mean it could
under certain circumstances so the rule
is you take or a simp rule would be you
take all of the conserved
quantities you take all the conserved
quantities and you fix them in other
words you measure them or some other way
you know what they are and then you
simply study the system subject to the
constraint that the conserved quantities
have certain
values okay um that's essentially the
structure of statistical mechanics
calculating probabilities of things
subject to constraints and those
constraints usually take the form that
some
quantity
uh is fixed some conserved quantity is
fixed one or more all right let's uh let
me give you an example that we could
make up using D dice D One
D no well okay
let's make up an example involving two
dice now I'm going to number the sides 1
2 3 four five six of course this one
also has a four five and a six but you
can't see it and this other one also has
a 1 two and three and you can't see it
and the rule is now they interact with
each other interacting with each other
means
that when one flips the other is also
forced to flip and the rule is they flip
in such a way that the sum of the
numbers on the two of them doesn't
change for example in this case we start
with two and six from two and six we can
flip in a way that can bring us to what
it can bring us to four and four it can
bring us to one and seven except there
is no seven uh it can bring us to three
and five but it cannot bring us to 1 and
two so that's a rule and we could write
that as a conservation law for each
value of the total number there would be
another closed cycle because you can't
get off the cycle you can't change the
total I don't know what to call number
here that's another generalized
zil uh the generalized zil here cannot
change and so therefore
the let's see how many possibilities are
there for the conserved quantity you can
have one and one you can have
two conserved quantity can be two it can
be three and what's the largest value it
can have
12 okay then it have to be seven in
order to to inide well if it was seven
then then you could any any 1 2 3 4 5
would
match subtracting from Seven would give
the other no you use all sides two is
just very constraining two is very
constraining yeah there's only one
configuration it happens there's only
one
configuration you there
two no they both have to have one that's
one
configuration this one being one and
this one being one 11 one's five the
other
Sixt that there are two there are two
way yeah there's two ways of making 11
but only one way of making
12 symmetry no okay just just the only
thing that counts is the number on top
uh all right you get the point all right
so I haven't told you what the
multiplicity of each uh value is this
only one here only one here one
configuration here what's a three you
can do with a one and a two or a two and
a one I think those are the only two
ways is that right right what about a
four
uh I think that's right so there's a
multiplicity of ways of doing it but
each one of
these numbers has associated with it a
cycle Let's uh for example the two cycle
the cycle associated with two what is
that
uh it
uh yeah you know okay
um yeah one one goes to one one that's
all that can happen it just stay in
other words it stays the same stays the
same what about the
three how many possibilities are there
for the motion within the three
cycle what are they let's
see one two goes to one
two or one two goes to
21 okay both of them are possible uh so
I think there's two uh two yeah so I
think what do we say oh uh sorry this is
the two cycle there were three states of
the three cycle what are they what no no
no
no two states of the three cycle yeah
yeah so it's one of these jobs like that
one goes to the other the other comes
back to it two two possible Cycles
or you just come back to the same thing
okay one of the other
and so forth there are a bunch of
different
disconnected
orbits the orbits in this case would be
characterized by the value of this
number and once you fix it then you can
throw away all the others and
concentrate on the little
subsystem which is uh contain which has
a particular value of the conserved
numbers all right is that clear
all right the most important cons
Quantum I keep saying quantum number the
most important conserved
quantity is energy and that's the one
where where most of our focus is going
to
be there are
others for example in
chemistry there are a lot of conserved
things the amount of each or the number
of atoms of each the number of atoms of
each uh element are conserved in
chemistry okay and nuclear physics of
course that's not true but the total
number of protons plus neutrons is
conserved so there are other uh
conserved quantities but as I said for
the most part energy will be our most
important
uh oh oh oh sorry sorry sorry sorry
let's go back a step let's go back a
step to information information plays a
very important role in what's going on
um I gave you a counter example to the
robustness of this namely the existence
of conserved quantum numbers conserved
quantities but obviously it's not really
a counter example you just have to
generalize a little bit but let me give
you now an example which is really much
worse and the much worse example goes
like this
red goes to
red yellow goes to red blue goes to Red
what do you think green goes to
red orange goes to
Red is there another one yeah blue blue
goes to
Red oh yeah but purple purple
good purple goes to Red that's a
perfectly good deterministic law it
tells you what happens next no matter
where you start you just get red all
right
um you start the system out
somewhere okay there are no conserved
quantities here no conserved quantities
they couldn't be if there was anyone any
conserved quantity it's very
quickly there's obviously no conserved
quantity they all have the same value
because they or whatever quantity you
pick because they can all get the red R
so they have to have the same value of
whatever it is as red does so there's no
conserved quantity that's not the
problem
here on the other hand it's certainly
true that at least over reasonable
lengths of time remember this thing
happens
fast if you intervene with a system
what's the most likely thing that you
find righted in fact not only is it the
most likely it's overwhelmingly more
likely it's infinite Ely more likely you
will simply find red you won't find any
of the
others here's an example where there are
no conserved quantities but it is not
true
nevertheless that there is equal a
priori probability of all of the
different values
of the uh the color index
here what's
wrong with this example well there's
nothing really wrong with it it's a it's
a possible world but it doesn't behave
the way real dynamical systems do real
dynamical systems have something that I
always call the conservation of
information but you could equally well
call it the conservation of
distinctions what it says in this simple
context is that distinctions between
configurations don't disappear distinct
beginnings
always give you distinct outputs
distinct starting points always give you
distinct uh
outputs and not only that if you trace
backward first of all it's deterministic
which means no matter where you start
you get to a very definite place after
each each uh instant and distinctions
don't merge in other words what you
would what this would look like would be
red goes let's see how to draw it
um red goes to red yellow goes to Red
obviously what happens here is the
different trajectories all merge they
all merge and come together with
red no matter what you start with red
yellow whatever you get out
red so in this case the trajectories
just merge together and because they
merge together initial distinctions are
lost you can call that loss of
information you can call it loss of
distinctions you can call it the
violation of the conservation of
information how about irreversibility
you can call it irreversibility but
irreversibility it is a form of
irreversibility but I don't want to
confuse it with thermodynamic
irreversibility thermodynamic
irreversibility is a different thing uh
and uh so I didn't want to call it that
but it is it is it's sort of the deepest
form of
irreversibility laws of physics which
lead deterministically to outputs but
the output doesn't determine the input
you can't get back to the input loss of
information in this case here it's quite
obvious that um that the a priori
probability of the different starting
points is not equal so that's is not uh
equal the the initial the a priority
probability so that's another counter
example and that's a
more dangerous kind of counter example
dangerous in the sense that if you had a
system like that it would not satisfy
the rules of statistical
mechanics uh the rules of statistical
mechanics are fundamentally based on the
idea that the microscopic laws of
physics the laws of physics which
govern at the deepest level and we're
going to be M mainly talking about
classical physics here uh at the deepest
level the molecular level or the atomic
level or the elementary partical level
or whatever level we have to get to to
to understand the system that the laws
are consistent with the conservation of
distinctions or the conservation
of uh are we saying the
change the sample size is not going to
change
no if you mean by the sample size the
volume of a system no you can yeah can
you describe this say a one to one
function yeah can is this going to be a
strong a restriction absolutely without
it we would get nowhere and what about
its physic
is it is it a good physical assumption
yes it's not only a good physical
assumption it's a consequence of the
basic principles of classical mechanics
and all classical physics all classical
physics is dependent on
it no no there's a there's a quantum
mechanical version of it there is a
quantum mechanical version of it in
classical physics it's called lille's
theorem I'm going to tell you what it is
in quantum mechanics it's called
unitarity but we're not going to be
doing very much quantum mechanics if we
do any quantum mechanics we'll probably
do some but we'll do a sort of seat of
the pants we won't use the the real
principles of quantum mechanics uh but
um
uh uh but the classical version of it I
will basically tell you right now I have
a question yeah so that's either away
right one t go to two different
states yeah I mean as somebody said back
there the conservation of distinctions
means that the mapping is one to
one so that example of the summations of
the GU is not
allowed oh yes the summation of
because may or may not because one state
of one two that could go back to the
same state it could go to a different
you have to postulate a law all right
now if in each if in each sector each
sector means each value of the conserved
quantities if the diagram in that sector
is a closed loop like that then you're
in business that conserves
distinctions if you start here you get
to here if you start here you get to
here you can tell not only where you're
going but where you came from that's the
characteristic of a system which
conserves distinctions if you know where
you are you not only know where you're
going to be next but you know where you
are last okay now in this case if you
know you're at Red you can ask where did
I where am I going next the answer is
red where did I come from beats me I
don't
know no way to tell so yeah you started
off by talking about coin flipping and
this seems to be going quite a different
way we're not talking about random
outcomes of a of something we're talking
about quite deterministic rules yes
we're talking yes the world the world at
least the classical world is
deterministic it's only apparently
statistical it's apparently statistical
and we're going to talk about the
conditions why it is apparently
statistical but I will tell you right
now it's apparently a system is
apparently St uh statistical typically
because it's coupled to a much much
bigger system about which you know very
little and a heat bath in other
words and you don't know enough about
the heat bath to um uh to
uh to specify the details of it but
that's always the case I mean uh that
things are random not always the case
but it's the case in classical physics
that things are random not because
there's any intrinsic Randomness in the
laws of physics but because you simply
don't know enough you don't specify
we're going we're going to talk about
that that's the basic idea of
entropy all right in any case this
principle of the conservation of
distinctions is so important it's rarely
mentioned because it is so deeply
assumed by everybody who does classical
physics that it is rarely mentioned as
one of the laws of
thermodynamics I would call it the
zeroth law of thermodynamics except the
zeroth law of thermodynamics is also
used for something else so we could call
it the minus first law of
thermodynamics and it is the most
Central fact that must be true for
thermodynamics or statistical mechanics
to make sense and for it to predict the
consequences of thermodynamics the
theory of heat so it's uh it's
I say built into the structure of
classical mechanics what is the what is
the relevant statement about classical
mechanics
um classical mechanics of course does
not deal with these very very trivial I
use these as illustration illustration
of a
concept um but of course classical
mechanics deals with continuous
systems systems of coordinates and
momenta are for our purposes now
momentum can just be mass times
velocity and uh each coordinate of a
system has associated with it a momentum
namely its time derivative times the
mass of the object uh and uh but of
course there is a deeper more profound
meaning to the idea of a momentum we've
talked about it in classical Mechanics
for the purpose of this class momentum
can just mean conventional
momentum although there may be
situations where you want to keep track
of a
more uh profound definition of momentum
all right so what is the state of a
system the state of a system for this
simple example of a single D was just a
label color State the color if you know
it and if you know the color you know it
comes next and you know it comes before
if it's a case of two dice then it's a
pair of the state of the system is
labeled by a pair of colors what about a
single point particle a single point
particle is labeled by a collection of
coordinates X Y and Z or X1 X2 X3 X Y
and Z the coordinates of the particle
and the corresponding momentum the X Y
and Z components of the momentum
equivalently the X Y and Z components of
the
Velocity but uh for reasons that go into
the depths of classical
mechanics uh the momenta are the right
things to describe it by the symbol for
momenta the historical symbol for
momentum is p and the historical symbol
for coordinate is of course
X there are three PS and three X's for
each particle so I draw it as just a p
and an X plane but of course for a
ordinary particle there would be a
three-dimensional P space and a three
dimensional X space so it gets
complicated fast to picture the phase
space this is called the phase space the
phase space of a classical
particle is six
dimensional what is the X space call
just X by itself without worrying about
P it's called a configuration space so
the configuration space is the space of
x's the phase space is the space of x's
and P
but what
constitutes a state of a particle is not
an X but an X and a p and the reason is
that in order to say where a particle is
going to be next you not only have to
know where it is but you have to know
how it's
moving okay you have to know both its
position and its momentum or the
position and velocity so for a single
particle the x's and the PS
are like the color of the edge of of of
the surface of the dice it labels a
state of the particle for many particle
system for many particle system there
are many x's and many PS if there are 10
particles how many X's are
there
30 X Y and Z for all 10 particles PX py
and pz for all 10 particles so what do
we say there were 30 X's 30 PS so for 10
particles 60 coordinates to the phase
space and so it gets uh gets complicated
fast for a system of 10 to the 23rd
particles I won't try to draw
it uh it's uh 6 * 10 23rd dimensional
space but now what does it mean to say
what first of all what is an orbit what
is a
history a starting point which could be
like the analog of starting with red is
just a starting point in this phase
space and then the equations of motion
either Newton's equations or whatever
equations are governing the
system allow you to follow it so you
follow it with time these little ticks
here could be microc seconds but of
course the motion is continuous but you
could nevertheless you could divide it
up into m Ms if you like
or uh what's smaller nanocs or whatever
you want to do and draw the trajectory
and that's the trajectory in the phase
space it's not the trajectory of the
object in space it's the trajectory
through this phase space wherever you
start oh there are various kinds of
situations and we can talk about them in
some of them the trajectories just
wander off and go to Infinity for
example just for a free particle a free
particle if you give it a shove it just
goes off to Infinity its momentum
doesn't change so p is constant but X
just goes off to Infinity but for the
kinds of systems we're interested in the
systems which are contained within
finite boxes as a rule the system uh
will
not um leak off to Infinity but it will
somehow use usually wind up coming
back uh or perhaps not coming back to
exactly the same point but uh
it that's a bad drawing that's not a
good drawing because it in it
illustrates something exactly the thing
which doesn't happen it illustrates
exact the problem the problem is two
Dimensions is too low a dimension to toh
to draw a good
picture okay what doesn't happen What
doesn't happen and now this is a theorem
of classical
mechanics and it has several pieces to
it the first statement is that
trajectories don't
merge never
happens all right this is the analog of
saying that distinctions are
preserved distinctions are conserved the
two different starting points never lead
to the same end point okay and also the
opposite is true of course this wouldn't
make any sense at all a given starting
point splits in two what on Earth would
that mean you start at some given
starting point and uh and you that would
mean it's not deterministic it would
mean you don't know where you go next
when you get to this point over here
those things don't happen trajectories
don't cross number one they don't cross
and number two they don't merge so
trajectory doesn't cross like that they
never do that and they never
merge now there can be conserved
quantities in other words the
trajectories can be labeled for example
with values of energy the energy doesn't
change along a trajectory it's much like
the zilch It doesn't change along the
trajectory and so the different
trajectories in general
whatever they
do may be labeled by the
energy and that energy doesn't change
you pick it once and for all and it
stays that way so that's again what is
that called that's called the
conservation of energy
yeah yeah well of course that that's
that's up to you how you want to Define
it but yes you can uh you can think of
it as going backward in time also start
no no no no but you could you could
um you could for convenience say let's
consider all the
Motions that start out at time T equals
z of course that allows you to start
anywhere it allows you to start anywhere
and so there's lots and lots of
trajectories but yes they can all also
go backward and you could label a whole
thing by uh by uh not label the whole
thing but you could draw the whole
entire trajectory both going backward
and
forward an
example just as a simple example which
is too simple for any interesting
statistical purposes a harmonic
oscillator where you have momentum let's
say position which did I do it I guess I
did momentum and position for harmonic
oscillator the trajectory is just a
that's not a very good ellipse it's
intended to be an ellipse the center of
the ellipse is at the center of the
diagram and the object and the point in
Phase space just goes around an ellipse
if you projected it onto the xaxis the
motion would just be going up and down
as an oscillator if you project it onto
the momentum axis which is the same as
velocity it would also be going back and
forth but there are many trajectories
and what distinguishes the uh yeah what
distinguishes these different
trajectories the energy the energy of
the
oscillator and also where you started
them but
uh um where they were at time T equals z
but these are the different trajectories
and as you can see they don't cross but
that's a general
principle so first of
all there's the principle from classical
mechanics that trajectories never cross
emerge now that's not quite good enough
for us here's a
situation that uh
still could happen even though
trajectories don't merge or cross you
could have a situation which in
practical in a practical sense is as bad
as merging namely where the trajectories
very rapidly come together they don't
quite ever merge but perhaps they get
exponentially closer and closer all
trajectories getting closer and closer
then for practical purposes you would
lose
distinctions uh no matter how good
you're resolving power was wait long
enough and you lose the distinction
between these different trajectories at
least from a practical point of view
that doesn't happen that doesn't happen
trajectories don't merge like that
either really merge in this
sense or do this kind of thing which may
look to you to your eye the same as this
but you can imagine the difference here
trajectories are just coming together
ASM totically that doesn't happen the
theorem this is called lille's theorem
we're not going to prove it
I don't remember if we proved it in the
classical mechanics class it's called
lille's
theorem not Louisville but
leoville Li
I leoville leoville
theorem lille's theorem says the
following that if you start with all of
the points in a patch of phase
space take all the points in a patch of
phase space start out the system at time
T equals
0 and follow each one of them for a
certain length of
time the volume of the patch of phase
space doesn't change with time the
volume stays the same that says that
even if the points in the phase space
might contract in one one dimension they
will spread out in the other dimension
in the other
direction uh and in that sense
distinctions are preserved the volume in
Phase space is conserved and that's
another that's the that's the um the
continuous version of the idea that
convergence of trajectories doesn't
happen that uh if you like that
information is not
lost or that distinctions are not lost
yeah could you compare area but have it
such that so complicated that it fills
up a huge yes that's the second law yes
that's exactly right that is the second
law of
Thermodynamics uh that that well the
increase of entropy is exactly that but
is that the reverse of this merging I
mean to say that it's not going to
merge merge picture backwards but that
give you well we we will come to this
this is an important
Point uh uh that
uh and let me state it for the rest of
the uh class here the question
was can it happen and the answer is it
almost always happens for interesting
systems of sufficient
complexity what can it happen that the
volume of this region does stay
conserved but it sort of branches out in
some horrible fractal
I don't know how to draw it I mean I'm
not very good at drawing
fractals in such a way that it
eventually apparently fills up the whole
phase
space uh and the answer is yes the
answer is yes that does tend to
happen no that cannot happen it
preserves its
topology yeah it preserves its topology
there are no
mergers but chaos happens this is called
chaos when this
happens what's required for the this is
since this a theorem what's the
requirements what what what are the
apul axioms to prove the theorem lungan
form of classical mechanics either the
lanan form the hamiltonian form or the
principle of least action okay so uh it
all traces back ultimately to the
principle of least action or if you like
lrange or Hamilton's forms of the
equations of of classical mechanics yeah
does the volume correspond to a a known
physical
conch uh
yes well yes or no um it's connected
with
entropy but entropy uh is a is a subtle
thing um all right let me let me State
what the bottom line is the bottom line
is
that if we have a system which is
enclosed so that it doesn't escape away
to infinity and it has the property the
pro it shares the property with uh these
kinds of
systems the kind of systems that are
represented by Cycles namely that there
are no
mergers and no splittings and that sort
of thing conservation of
information
then if the system moves through the
phase space fast enough or in other
words or equivalently if you wait an
average over long enough
times then there is equal a priori
probability subject to the constraints
subject to the constraint of the
conservation of energy which means
that you study
only surfaces in this phase space which
correspond to fixed energy fixed energy
might correspond to a surface in the
phase space moving around the Subspace
of the phase space then a priori
probabilities are simply
uniform in the phase space it's another
way of saying that if you time average
things over time long by comparison with
some appropriate time then the average
over time is simply the average over the
phase Bas or equivalently equal a priori
probabilities to every point on the
phase space subject to the constraints
so that provides you leil theorem
provides you with kind of
the
um basic
notion of a priori
probability equal statistical weights to
every point in the phase space um
measured by the volume or every volume
of phas space of the same volume has
equal probability so in some sense it's
it doesn't have a different uh density
yeah that's right the density is the
density is uniform on the on the phase
space the sort of a priori probability
density is uniform on on
face are you saying
that I mean are you saying it's erotic
I'm yeah I'm assuming that the system is
erotic okay so erotic means all right so
yeah I'm assuming that um and it's true
for almost all systems um well actually
I am I'm actually not assuming it's
erotic if it's not erotic it means that
there are extra conserved
quantities when a system is not
erotic that means that the phase space
divides up into different pieces which
carry different conserved quantities
then you have to pick a value of the
conserved quantities so for example for
the harmonic oscillator that's not
erotic what does erotic mean I'll just
tell you very briefly erotic is fairly
closely related to chaotic it's not
exactly the same thing thing but it
means that the phase Point wanders
around rather uh thoroughly throughout
the phase
space and uh pretty much touches every
point on the phase base very much
like this touches every Point by the
time it gets back okay if it doesn't
touch every
point then that means that there are
closed sectors which have conserved
quantities which correspond to conserved
quantities for example this this phase
space is not at all erotic this point
doesn't get to every Point inside here
it only gets to the points on the same
ellipse but that just tells you that
there are conserved quantities there's a
conserved quantity which takes on a
value on every
ellipse if you fix that conserved
quantity then you stay on a given
ellipse if you calculate the time
average as the phase Point moves around
that ellipse
that average quantity will be the same
as calculating the average over the
ellipse the time average will be the
same as averaging over points on the
ellips so in fact really I have not so
much assumed
erity as I've assumed when you say there
are no additional conserved quantities
besides Energy that really is the
statement of erotic uh Behavior
okay
um yeah your statement of theem you talk
about the volum of the points in the in
Phase space not in ordinary coordinate
space not in um okay so let's let's just
remember what fa what a volume in Phase
space means is it's a thing with
units of uh let's say let's say it's a a
simp a simple particle one particle then
a volume in space has units of length
cubed a volume in phas space has units
of length cubed time momentum cubed it's
a six-dimensional little volume element
and has units of length times momentum
which is called
action okay uh length cubed times
momentum cubed is called action cubed uh
so it's volume in Phase space not volume
in ordinary
space I was going to say uh point
doesn't have any
volume right well what's that's true h
no no no and what I say is you start
with a little volume in Phase space
little or big it doesn't matter and you
track all the
points and you see where they
go this had a volume this has a
volume fix time yeah fix time right but
the volume of this will be exactly the
same as the volume of that in the case
of the harmonic oscillator just the
ellipse just stays the same so therefore
that be an example
of but don't you need an infinite number
of points that a to show that there's a
volume otherwise how can you yeah an
infinite number of points a volume are
you are you are you fo are you fooled by
the fact that I drew some points here oh
no no no no I just you
know no no no no no it's it's a
continuous it's a
volume it's a volume in the phas Bas I
just I could cross-hatch it okay does
that make it
better is that related to the fact that
you have one to one mapping you have a
point in one state yes yes yes yes again
again the the motion of dynamical
systems the initial State at one time is
related to the final State at another
time as a onetoone mapping right as a
onetoone mapping and in that sense it is
like
this all
right okay and just as this if you cycle
around here long enough you will average
over all these points with equal a prior
probability uh the same is uh the same
is true of following uh points and face
base and the right statement at the end
is that the a priori probability the a
priori measure whatever you would like
to call it for a dynamical system is
volume in Phase
space well let me let me just point out
that that you can you can map the unit
circle to the circle of radius 2 and
that does not preserve area right but it
does it is 1: one it is 1: one you're
right you're right that's uh okay good
good good it's yeah that that that's
right that's right it's more than one:
one it's more than one:
one um it's volume preserving or or
phase Space volume
preserving which is better than one: one
how
you well you don't I mean we're doing
classical physics now if we were doing
quantum mechanics we would subdivide the
phas space into little boxes of order H
bar on a
side and uh we would think about little
boxes in Phase space which were no
better defined than uh than the
uncertainty principle allows so actually
perspective aite number of points well a
finite density of them in any case
yeah right right
good and uh as I said that's why I don't
uh at this point want now the ultimate
justification in fact for this principle
that of equal a priority probability on
phase space really is quantum
mechanics um because it's only in
quantum mechanics where the states of a
system are discrete and where you can
actually
count you can actually count States and
so forth and uh make it more like this
situation here all right that uh in any
case that's an important principle that
equal a priority probabilities or
uniform a prior probability
distribution um let's talk about
probabilities and get to
entropy
okay we've discussed energy energy is a
conserved
quantity
we fix the conserved quantity called
energy for a
system and then Within
the space of a particular value of
energy the system May hop around from
one state to another all with the same
energy and as it hop hops around if it
hops around fast enough you get to
average or you get to ask about
probabilities by asking how much time
does the system spend in each one of its
particular
configurations and that by lille's
theorem will pretty much be guaranteed
to be just average over the phase
space okay the next concept is
entropy now you might have thought the
next Concept in thermodynamics would be
temperature temperature is much more
intuitive than
entropy well is it it's really not um
you have of course a body sense of what
temperature
is uh things are hot and things are cold
and so you have an I I don't think you
have an intuitive sense of what
temperature means but you do have an
intuitive sense of what hot and or at
least a biological sense of what hot and
cold
is but it's really energy and entropy
which are the more basic concepts so
let's start let's talk about
entropy
okay before we talk about entropy let's
talk about probability distributions
if we have some variable and that
variable could be the numbers on a
die or it could be a continuous
variable such as X or P or something
else then you may have a probability
distribution of some kind where you got
it from let's not worry about where you
got it from this is some variable it may
be a collection of variables there may
be more than one of them but let's just
take a one dimensional thing here's the
probability p goes this way and the
probability distribution I don't know it
might be like that and every value of
the coordinate or the set of coordinates
by coordinates I now just mean any
parameters which describe the state of a
system as I said it could be the numbers
on a die if it was the numbers on a die
they would be discreet and instead of
having a continuous function for the
probability you would have just
sort
of set of numbers for the
probability the only difference between
the discret system and the continuous
system is whereas you might
add uh whenever you add for the discrete
system you're probably going to wind up
integrating for the uh for the
continuous system but we'll come back to
that all right
uh what does it take to be a probability
distri possible probability
distribution two things P must be
positive everywhere in both these cases
negative probabilities have no meaning
it could be zero of course when I say
positive I could also mean zero and the
other thing in this case is the sums of
the
probabilities let's call it P of I I now
is which particular State you're talking
about right sum of P sub I is equal to
one so a sum of positive things bunch of
positive things whose sum is one clearly
each one of the PS has to be less than
one less than or equal to one if the sum
of positive things adds up to
one uh each one must be less than or
equal to one the only way any one of
them can be equal to one is if all the
others are
zero the analogous situation for a
continuous variable is that the integral
of the probability let's call this
variable x p of X
DX is equal to
one and of course the way we use a
probability distribution is we don't
talk about the probability of a specific
value of the coordinate we talk about
the
probability that the coordinate X lies
between X and X+
DX we talk about the
probability that the coordinate lies in
a little interval
here and that naturally brings us to the
idea of a probability density a
probability density is a thing that we
integrate a probability for a discrete
variable is a thing that we sum right
our next concept another important
concept is the concept of the average
value of a quantity now I'm going to
assume of course that everybody knows a
little bit of
Statistics let's take uh let's take this
case here the discret case suppose that
there is some function
of I let's see what could we take it
to
um
H that could be I squ yeah just some
function of I well I I could be an
integer I of course could be many many
variables I've drawn it as one variable
but it could be a multi-dimensional
space some function some quantity which
depends on the state of the system could
be the
energy uh it could be anything that you
like any property of the system which if
you know I you know the value of that
property what do we call that let's call
that let's call a quantity the property
F and F also o depends on
I if you know the state of the system
then you know F what is the average
value of F and we'll label the average
value of
f by just a notation standard notation
for averages standard physicist
notation uh bracket around it that's the
average of f what's the definition of
the average the definition is to sum up
over all I
F of I but weighted with the
probability for that value of
I remember the PS add up to
one that's the definition of the average
value of a quantity and it is the
standard average it's the ordinary
average except
weighted by the probability not just by
a flat measure not just adding up the F
subis and dividing but uh but um but
weighting them according to P ofi why do
you weit it according to P of I well you
can imagine a situation for example
where you had only one one nonzero
probability you wouldn't want to if you
wanted the average value of f it's quite
clear the average value of f is just the
value of F at that point if you look at
this formula that's what you'll get all
the PS are equal to either zero or one
in this case and you'll only get one
contribution
so that's called the
average and now what I want you to
imagine as I said I do want you to keep
in mind that there could be this this
space here could be a multi-dimensional
space of some kind but I've enumerated
all of the states of the system here
enumerated them all laid them out
here and let's suppose now that all we
know about this system the only thing we
know
is that it's in
one of
moss States let's Suppose there are n
States
altogether m is less than n and all we
know about the system is that it's in
one of these M States so could be this
set of M States over
here that's all we
know what is the
probability out
here zero so the probability is of zero
out
here what about out
here and what about in
here not
one one
M remember they have to add up to one
so this is M States in here all we know
that is that it's in this range here and
the probability in here is 1/
M
question that when I say we know we know
nothing but that's another way of saying
they're equally
probable yeah if we know nothing but the
fact that it's in one of these M
states that that mean and we really just
don't know anything else then it's
equally probable that it's in any one of
these
M okay if it's equally probable that
it's in any one of these m a statement
of a complete ignorance is equivalent to
the statement that all things are
equally
probable right so a statement of
complete ignorance other than that we
know that the system is in one of these
m one of one of these M States is
equivalent to saying that we have a
probability distribution let's draw it
over
here which is zero
everywhere except in this range where
the probability distribution is 1/
M
right
okay um this m
here is a measure of our ignorance the
bigger m is the bigger our ignorance now
why might we be ignorant there may be
many reasons for being
ignorant uh but the usual
reason is because the number of degrees
of
freedom first of all they're very
microscopic second of all they are very
numerous and so typically there's lots
and lots of ignorance about a
system and all you know is some
restricted information now in this case
I've drawn a very very uh idealized
version of that idea where I know
nothing except that it's in one of these
one over M States m is a measure of your
ignorance but is it the only possible
measure of your ignorance no you could
take M2 you could take M cubed you could
take any monotonically increasing
function of
M and that would also be a measure of
your
ignorance the one which is called
entropy
is the logarithm of
M okay logarithm is a monotonically
increasing function log
M and it's called s s for entropy why is
s entropy I don't know uh is
logarithm of M for this particular case
over here it's logarithm of M or if you
like it's within this well okay it's
logarithm of M which is also Al equal
incidentally notice uh that it's equal
to minus logarithm of 1 / M the only
reason I'm writing in terms of 1/ M is
because the probability distribution
happens to have height 1/ M all right so
this is writing it in terms of logarithm
of the probability distribution in here
logarithm of the probability where it's
not zero in N A non zero range that is a
measure of urance yeah does matter what
the base of the L it's a natural lthm
yeah we're going to in fact you could
you have your choice about how you want
to Define it and in different branches
of science it's defined in different
bases in physics it's always log to the
base e natural logarithm in information
Theory it's usually log to the base two
but the conversion factor is just a
factor of logarithm of two right the
logarithm of a yeah so it's a trivial
relationship in information Theory
people like using binary digits and they
like taking powers of
two uh an entropy of logarithm of two is
called well logarithm of two in this
sense in the natural log two is called
one bit we'll come to why it's called a
bit but
uh but in any case this is the ENT now
why I take the logarithm I'm not going
to tell you right now why we take the
log logarithm the answer is because it's
useful um to take the
logarithm what's
that just told us yeah I'm not going to
tell you why it's useful yet yet we are
certainly going to find out why all
right I will tell you I will tell you
yeah all right let's let me I will tell
you by
example let's do an example
supposing I have a bunch of coins in
coins Big N coins in
coins Each of which can be heads or
tails that's my system my system is not
a single coin my system is in
coins heads Tails Tails heads and so
forth okay and supposing I know nothing
about it let's take the most extreme
example of ignorance I don't know
nothing okay what's the
entropy well how many configurations are
there all together two to the
end what's the logarithm of
that
H and log two
notice that the entropy now is
proportional to the number of coins it
makes sense now to talk about the
entropy per coin the entropy per coin is
logarithm of two by taking the logarithm
we reduce entropy to something which is
additive which adds up over the system
which is proportional to the size of the
system for
example the entropy in this room room is
proportional to the number of molecules
in the room but the only reason that
it's proportional to the number of
molecules in the room is because I've
taken this logarithm so here's an
example if the molecules were just
replaced by coins and the only question
was is the coin a head or a tail you can
see that by taking the logarithm you
make something which is proportional to
the number of degrees of
freedom uh so entropy like energy is
something which adds up for system yeah
and in that's say it
again yeah in base two that would just
be n good in base 2 it would just be n
in base e it's n log
2 but in any case in either case one bit
of information means either when we're
talking about base e it means a entropy
of log 2 or when we're talking about to
the base two it's a just means an
entropy of one
unit uh the entropy of a single coin if
we didn't know whether it was heads or
tails that's called a bit so entropy is
measured in bits yeah is there a precise
definition of the degree of
freedom I I
but a
variable how do you know how many
degrees of Fe something
has well you ask how many variables are
there that you have to know
in this case the variable is either head
or tail head tail and you need to know
any of
them I I imagine we can concoct some
more official
definition but I can't think I can't
think of a I can't think of it right
right more or less in your examples
you're getting the number of particles
CU that's kind of was flowing well in
the case of in the case of um in the
case of a single particle of course it's
six the three coordinates and right so
more or less yes yeah wait a minute you
said we know zil in this case but you
didn't take that into account yeah in
this case we don't know zilch in this
case we don't know
zilch right the case if you double the
number of coins then uh then you double
the INRI so that would be an argument
for using the law with it because yeah
that's yeah that's the idea that
um now an exercise you could ask is
supposing you did know the zil then what
would the entropy
be then there would be some states right
right take
averages need one more thing if you know
something in additional you know
probabilities take an average um of that
La quantity absolutely absolutely that's
called yeah
absolutely well we're going to take an
average of this quantity yeah
precisely precisely but I
um you got me so excited with that
remark that I forgot my train of
thinking
um
yeah it was it was a tremendously
important point and I forgot what it is
well I don't remember what it is but
let's just do one a couple more examples
um again supposing we oh oh oh one yeah
I remember what the important point
is supposing we know everything about
the
system knowing everything would mean in
this case we know exactly which
configuration we're in
that would
mean that one of these states has
probability
one and all the others have zero What's
the entropy
then zero it's just log of One log of
one is
zero okay e to the 0 is one so this is a
kind of interesting fact when you have
complete in information that's equ
equivalent to zero entropy when you have
no information that's when you have the
maximum entropy incidentally you cannot
have a ma an entropy bigger than this
this is easy to
prove
um
sorry logarithm of n this one is the
largest entropy you can have for that
case
um
so entropy is a measure of ignorance now
this is interesting notice that with
this definition of entropy and it is the
real definition of entropy it is not
really a function of the properties of a
system it's a function not only of the
system but your state of knowledge of
the system now that sounds a little bit
ridiculous because entropy is something
we're going to treat as though it were a
quantity uh associated with the system
and we'll come to why but really it's a
it's it's a joint question of the
system it's uh probability distribution
in fact it's a function of the
probability distribution is what it
is okay so that's uh that's the
simple-minded notion of entropy over
here now let's try to find a definition
going exactly in the direction that you
pointed out a moment
ago let's imagine some probability
distribution I don't mean it to be
continuous I just don't want to draw a
bunch of vertical lines a probability
distribution now which is not flat and
then zero but
um may have some width maybe close it
may be that it's close to zero in some
region in some range and then close to
one for some other range and then close
to zero but it's not exactly zeros and
ones it's a more complicated or arbit in
fact probability
distribution can we generalize this
idea so that we have a measure of
ignorance which is in some sense
approximately a notion of the number of
states that we've included under the
probability distribution here which have
non- negligible probability the
logarithm of it all right so here's the
usual
definition it's actually the average
the average here it is log of 1/ M it's
the average of
logarithm of the
probability the average of the logarithm
of the probability now wait a minute
minus remember that the probability is
always between zero and one what does
that mean about the
logarithm negative just like the
logarithm of 1 / m is negative here so
that means that this is positive
it's the average of the logarithm of the
probability of the I
configuration okay how do we calculate
that well we just use the formula for
averages where do I have the formula for
averages I think I lost it so let's
write it
down the average of a function of
I is equal to the sum of I of f of I * P
of I
let's apply that let's calculate the
average of the logarithm of the
probability that's equal now for f of I
now we just substitute minus log P sub I
so what is it it's just summation of
I of
minus P sub I as this one times log of P
sub I
that's called this is it this is the
final definition of
entropy let's look at it for a moment
supposing we have one of these
distributions which is flat and
zero equal to 1/ M up on the
top and it encloses m States Al together
what is this
quantity
well outside when we start adding up the
contributions to it there are
contributions from the regions where p
is zero they give zero because p is
equal to zero on the other hand there
are the contributions from within this
range and what are they given by they're
given by let's see what they are p ofi
is 1/ M for each one of those
States then this
logarithm of one
M A minus
sign and now we have to sum over
I but each one of the states in this bin
here gives the same answer so what do we
do with
it we multiply it by m we multiply it by
the number of states here that just
cancels out
this and gives us minus log 1 / M which
is the same as log
M so so this formula the average of the
log of the
probability reproduces this formula for
a square distribution like this but it's
more
General and it is kind of a measure of
the width of the distribution or the
number of
configurations with non- negligible more
or less equal non-g neg negligible
probabilities but it is what it is P ofi
log p ofi is called the
entropy
okay as I said it
reproduces this
answer when the conditions are
applicable for this answer and otherwise
it gives a general
answer any
questions yeah don't you have to add in
the coefficient of resps uh constant to
make it consistent with classical
thermodynamics in which you have
boltzman's
constanton boltzman's
constant
absolutely yeah I always forget about
boltzman's
constant right okay so let me let me
uh
right boltzman's
constant traces back to the definition
of temperature energy and entropy
together determine
temperature
um in the early days when
physicists or whoever they would called
themselves at that
time uh steam Engineers whoever it was
were interested in temperature they
really didn't know what temperature
was all they knew was how you measure it
measure it with
thermometers uh in the beginning they
didn't even have the idea of an absolute
zero of
temperature but uh today we know
temperature is a form of energy or is it
is measured in unit of energy the
appropriate idea of for example the
temperature of a gas is a measure of the
energy of individual
molecules not exactly but that's roughly
what it is the conversion factor between
energy which was measured in
jewels and temperature was which was
measured in degrees uh what Celsius or
degrees Kelvin or whatever the
conversion factor was not known it
wasn't known how much energy per
molecule there was in a gas at a certain
temperature so there was an unknown
conversion factor boltzman introduced it
he was the one who realized boltzman and
Maxwell realized that at least for a gas
or an ideal gas temperature is a measure
of the kinetic energy of the
molecules but the UN unnown conver and
why was there an unknown conversion
factor basically because they didn't
know how many molecules there were in a
mole of
gas they knew how much energy they could
measure how much energy does it take to
heat up a mole of gas one degree but
what they didn't know is they didn't
know how many molecules were there so
boltzman's constant which was a measure
of the energy per molecule that was
unknown um if we use today we know of
course how many molecules there are in a
mole of
gas and we can work if we like with
units of temperature which are really
just units of energy we can measure
temperature in Jewels it's just the
energy needed uh the energy um of a
single particle roughly speaking the
energy of a single particle in a gas at
that
temperature so that's just a historical
fact boltzman did not know his own
constant um boltzman was so depressed by
the fact that he didn't know his own
constant that he committed suicide and I
think the next year Einstein figured out
what boltzman's constant was from the
uh
uh brownie motion yeah I don't think
that's the reason boltzman considered
suicide did suicide I don't know why he
did Newton also didn't know his own
constant
yeah yeah took many years for Newton's
constant to be measured took few years
for boltzman's constant to be
measured know know his yeah yeah plk
know
his abut can we partition the constants
can we partition the constants those
constant where the person whose name is
attached to it knew what the Conant was
that's a con how many constants are
there
um let's see there was
a one of the hard ones that took a
little bit of time was uh the electric
charge what was known and easy to
measure was the ratio of the charge to
mass and then it took some time until
what's his name figured out Michael no
not Michaelson moley um milikin milikin
figured out how to measure the charge
separately from the mass so
whoever thought of the idea that
electrons had electric
charge didn't uh didn't know the value
of the
charge right who was that who uh who was
the first one who postulated that
electrons had
charge oh that there were electrons and
they had
charge yeah I think it was Benjamin
Franklin no I think it was Benjamin
Franklin I don't think it was Ronald
Reagan I think it was Benjamin Franklin
I don't know where that came
from
what B inv the
electron all right so we have now the
concepts of temperature
and
entropy and I've introduced the idea of
a probability
distribution now we're going to go
further next time but uh for
today let's just
postulate something called thermal
equilibrium for a
system now let me first explain
when a system can be said to be in
thermal equilibrium these are not
necessary in sufficient conditions this
is necessary condition but for many
systems it's sufficient
for lots of systems this is good
enough thermal equilibrium is not a
property of an isolated system if you
have a truly isolated ated
system it's not in thermal
equilibrium it has an
energy it has a definite value of the
energy you may not know what it is but
it has some energy that energy is fixed
thermal equilibrium is a property of a
system in
contact I'll tell you what contact means
in a
minute a system a in contact with a much
bigger system
B A doesn't stand for anything this is
not Alice and Bob this is a and
b uh a just stands for the system under
consideration b stands for heat bath
bath it's a very big system with many
many more degrees of
freedom and the whole system the whole
combined system of a the thing of
interest and B the heat
bath has a given total energy that's an
assumption for our purposes
the bigger system can be thought of as a
closed and isolated system let me say
what closed and isolated
means it means there's no way for energy
to flow into it and out of it either
it's contained within insulating walls
that don't allow any heat energy in or
out or it's just an isolated region in
space that nothing nothing can come into
or out
of the bath plus a can be an isolated
system but a is not an isolated
system now if the bath is big enough
basically in the limit oh oh one another
thing the bath plus a is isolated but
neither a nor the bath themselves are
isolated but they weakly
interact weakly interact means that the
energies of
interaction whatever the whatever the
interaction between A and B are it's
governed by some energies of interaction
the energies of interaction are very
small compared to the energy of either A
or B but the interactions whatever they
are allow energies to go back and forth
from A to
B they allow energies to be transferred
back and forth
from B to a from A to
B the whole system has a definite energy
so the whole system has a definite value
of the zilch the zilch being energy in
this
case that whole system will move around
in its phase space on a surface of
constant energy but it'll move around
and hop around from point to point from
point to point and among other
things the different points will
correspond to different ways of
partitioning the given amount of energy
into the energy of the heat bath and the
energy of
a so under these
circumstances neither the energy of the
heat bath which we're not terribly
interested in nor the energy of a which
we are interested in will have a
definite predictable value it will
fluctuate it will have a probability
distribution a probability distribution
if you wait long long
enough until just wait long enough
that's it I mean there some time
scale uh of course if you start the
system some arbitrary
way it won't be in thermal equilibrium
but if you wait a long time until it
equilibrates and energy is hopping back
and forth between them uh in a long time
average
sense there will be a probability for
the energy of a
okay let's and in other words in other
words the various configurations of a
let's plot
them here are the various States the
energy states of a values of the energy
this is energy
now they may be discreet they may be
continuous not important for us at the
moment these are all the various values
that the energy of a this is the energy
of a I can take
on we start with a given total amount of
energy okay the energy of a will be a
small fraction of
it but as a function of the total energy
as a function of the total energy there
will be some probability
distribution and we can also think of it
as a function of the average energy
within a
whatever the energy of the whole system
is there will be the bigger the energy
of the whole system of course the bigger
the energy the average energy of a is
likely to
be so we can
parameterize the behav the nature of the
system by the average energy in a or by
the total energy if we know one we know
the other if we know the total energy in
principle we should if we know how to
calculate calculate the average energy
of a we'll learn how to do that right so
the average energy of a or the total
energy either one but let's say the
average energy of a this is the average
energy of
a or just the energy of a just the
a has some probability distribution and
this probability distribution is a
function not only of the energy of
a but also the average energy of a if
you give me an average energy of a then
there will be some probability
distribution so let's just think of a
probability
distribution which is parameterized in
other words it's a whole sequence of
different probability distributions the
different probability distributions
correspond to different values of the
overall
energy yeah the average of a is taken
over time
yes it can be taken over time yes it's
taken over time the average energy of a
is taken over time all right so it's
parameter you have a probability
distribution
which in fact we can just say it's a
function of the state of this of a and
the total energy if you
like the total energy parameterizes
the probability distribution change the
energy you change the probability
distribution of
a over its states the states of a or
I here are two things you can calculate
if you know the probability distribution
you can calculate the average energy of
e of
a and you can calculate also the entropy
given a probability distribution you can
calculate the entropy of a
extens P of a which happens to be the
average of the log of the probability of
a with a minus sign in other words you
can calculate the average energy and
the
entropy now I'm going to tell you what
temperature
is what temperature
is if you
increase the energy of the system
of the combined
system if you increase it needless to
say and obviously the energy in a will
increase a little bit if you increase
the energy of the whole system a little
bit in general the entropy will also
change the entropy in a will also change
if you increase the energy of the whole
system and you can ask how much energy
how much change of energy in a does it
take
to change the entropy by one
bit how
much how
much change in EA how much change in the
energy of a must you make in order to
change S by one bit what is that that's
the change in energy the derivative of
the
energy with respect to the
entropy times that one bit which is
logarithm of two or something that's not
this is not the important thing
here that's how much energy you have to
add to a and how do you do it you add
the energy to a by adding it to the
whole heat bath here that changes the
average energy
EA and how much must you change EA in
order to change CH the entropy by one
bit in other words to hide one more bit
of information to increase your
Ignorance by one bit of of information
how much energy do you have to put into
a this derivative the change in energy
per unit entropy is called the
temperature that's what that's what's
called the temperature
T it's the
energy change
needed if you like to State it
colorfully to hide one more bit of
information but technically it's the
change in the entropy per unit entropy
of the
system okay so from an information
theoretic point of view it's the change
in the entropy if you hide an extra bit
of an example of it
incidentally is land hour's principle in
uh in uh
computing that if you want to erase a
bit of information from a computer now
remember you can't destroy
information you can't destroy
information because it's conserved
because of the principle of um
conservation of
distinctions so if you try to erase a
bit of information from the computer you
wind up putting it into the heat bath
surrounding the
computer all right how much heat or
energy do you put into the heat bath by
taking one bit of information out of
your computer and putting in the heat
bath
well it's the temperature times
logarithm of
two that's the amount of energy that
that's the amount of heat energy that
you put into the environment when you
erase a bit of information that's an
example of
it uh and that's why you can't erase
information from your computer without
putting heat into the envir IR
M why because when you erase a bit of
information you change s a little bit
well you can see why you can see why
there people working on revers yeah yeah
but if you yes right that means you do
your computation without
erasing right but if you
erase you will heat the
environment yeah
what's
that I missed I missed the uh you can
heat your house by erasing your
information what you can't do is cool
your house by opening the
refrigerator is really a small amount
of terms of an
environment yeah
right right okay so let's so let's say
now where the smallness comes in the
smallness comes in for exactly the
reasons that were asked to me a few
minutes ago what happened to boltzman's
constant the answer is really strictly
speaking boltzman's constant goes here
KB I'm inclined to work in
units just like when I do relativity I
work in units in which C is equal to one
uh um when I do thermodynamics and
statistical mechanics I always work in
units in which the boltzman constant is
equal to one but in ordinary units
ordinary units which are what they're
Jewels per degree uh
um K is Jewels per degree Kelvin yeah
right right it's a terribly small number
what is it anybody remember 10us 23
right like avagadro's number no inverse
of aagadu number right so it's um it's a
very very small number and this means
when you erase one bit of information at
a temperature T this is the this
temperature incidentally is the
temperature of the
surroundings when you erase a bit of
information you change the energy of the
surroundings by a very small
amount so K is a small
number uh and
yes so and it's also true that entropy
the
standard thermodynamic definition of
entropy let's see
um what I call entropy differ from the
standard entropy also by a fact of a
boltzman constant but is it upstairs or
downstairs
um uh I forget
isn't that a little bit of a circular
definition since in order to Define FS
you have to eliminate the states want
say that again isn't a circular
definition which um that one bit of
information is erased If U under that
situation since in order to Define s you
had
to enumerate the states which me that
you enumerate the bits
well I I don't think it's a circular
statement to say that if I erase a bit
of information from the computer it
heats the Atmosphere by a certain
amount um well in order to find s you
got in order to find F which is f s the
the enty S which s s s yes
right iate the states and the enumerate
B you don't have to know anything about
the computer you don't have to know
anything
you don't have to enumerate the States
you don't even have to know what the
states of the system are it's just a
general fact that if you erase one bit
of information from any computer no
matter what its states are and no matter
how it's made and what company it's made
by it will always heat The Atmosphere by
that
much so is it a circular statement not
no I don't think it's a circular
statement
um look St statistical mechanics is in a
certain sense a bunch of toies it's
mathematics okay when we apply it to
physics we're adding something else in
and we're adding in this idea of
averaging over times and so
forth
uh but I I didn't want to get into
landow's principle of what happens when
you erase a bit of information I simply
wanted to give you the definition of
temperature temperature is the change in
the energy that you must add had in
order to change the entropy by one bit
which means uh no
by divided by log two when we were
thinking about the D and thinking well
we're only interested in one face okay
we were making a choice about what
information was considered relevant okay
and it's not necessarily the same thing
that the computer user thinks of as a
bit that causes the chips to get
hot so that's a different
bit
um they they're probably related by some
constant I'm saying that chips that have
lots of cells get hot very there's a
certain amount of energy that we would
call a certain amount of entropy okay
but that's not the same thing as what in
the computer you would call
because there a lot there's a lot of
other stuff going on right yeah no the
actual the actual statement the correct
statement of landow's principle is you
will heat the Atmosphere by at least
this
much there's a very idealized
situation where only this very very
simplest thing happens namely without
the disturbing it any other way you
reject one bit landow's principal said
that's the absolute minimum that uh that
the energy of the atmosphere will change
by if you erase a bit of
information yeah is the
numerator isn't it the is the numerator
e the average energy yeah the average
energy of a so it should really have bra
yes it
should and I'm going to get tired of
writing the
average from now on whenever we think
about a quantity associated with a
subsystem
here I will often neglect to write
average but when we're thinking about
the subsystem in equilibrium with the
bath what we mean by the various
quantities associated with it is the
averages and they fluctuate they do
fluctuate uh and we're going to talk
about calculating fluctuations
fluctuations are an important thing in
fact that's what Einstein realized
Einstein
realized that uh that the quantities of
thermodynamics
fluctuate he realized that those those
fluctuations would have effects on small
little impurities in the system and
knock them
around and what he did was essentially
calculate the
fluctuations uh using statistical
mechanics fluctuations of various
quantities like pressure and energy and
so forth and demonstrated how they would
affect uh small impurity in a
system okay we've gone we've done quite
a bit we've gotten energy
entropy
temperature phase
space all right the next time we will
work
out and derive the boltzman distribution
the boltzman distribution is the
probability distribution for the states
of a in the heat
bath and it's obtained statistically by
using some probability arguments about
energy being transferred back and forth
between the system and the giant heat
bath
okay for more please visit us at
stanford.edu